Guide to the Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Interviews, 2010-2019 MS2388
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Interview: Brecher, Jeremy, 2013 October 12; MS2388
  Historian of labor struggles who was an antiwar activist, a regional organizer for SDS, an Associate Fellow at IPJeremy Brecher was a student activist living in Washington DC from 1965-70. He later became a labor historian, a documentary filmmaker and a writer on social change. He has authored more than a dozen books, including Strike, a history of American labor.S, and an active community organizer in the DC suburbs in the late 60s and early 70s.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Jeremy Brecher interview: Institute for Policy Studies in 1960s, Emergency Committee on the Transportation Crisis (ECTC), Women Strike for Peace (WSP) pioneered direct action, model for Code Pink, Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), DC Statehood Party, Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC), 1960s characterized by big national movements, Role of Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) and Weatherman, Black uprisings of 1967-68, Mistakes made by anti-war movement.
- Interview: Brown, Dale, 2015 October 22; MS2388
  High school activist who was arrested distributing anti-Vietnam War material at a military base. Also headed up a students' committee against the war in 1971 for May Day, an attempted shut-down of the US government by the peace movement.
  Keywords provided by donor for Dale Brown interview: Dale Brown, High school activism around constitutional rights, Vietnam War, The Mobilization for Survival ("The Mobe"), Mobe promoted separate student event for April 1971 national demonstration, Brown recruited students for anti-war events at Winston Churchill HS, other schools, Most schools gave High School students a hard time, threatened them with expulsion, Risks that students faced in expressing opposition, Getting arrested at Fort Meade by military police in 1971, for leafletting the military, Successful mass leafletting by Maryland and DC HS students for April-May 1971 demonstrations.
- Interview: Cassell, Charles, 2013 June 07; MS2388
  Prominent hometown civil rights activist; active in picketing D.C stores that wouldn't hire blacks, and in the anti-freeway fight; co-founder D.C. Statehood Party, and later D.C. Board of Education member, and chair of the historic D.C. Statehood Constitutional Convention.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Charles Cassell interview: Carl Hansen, schools' track system, Julius Hobson, William Kunstler, 1924 – born, 707 Fairmont Street, Albert I. Cassell (Cassell's father), Doc Stratton, Cassell's mother, Howard University, Lansburgh's, Hecht's, James Monroe School, Lucretia Mott School, Miner Teacher's College, Garnet–Patterson Jr. High School, Mr. Savoy, jazz, Louis Armstrong, Duke Ellington, Towson, MD, Charlottesville, VA, Cousin Wilkes, father "Al the Bookworm", Howard University, Hampton Institute, Ithaca, Ithaca High School, Professor George Young, World War I, father enlisted, France, 75 mm and 100mm cannon, Cornell, Bethlehem, PA, Alfred Wiener, George Washington Carver, Tuskegee, Howard University, African American architects, architectural department, School of Architecture, dean of Howard Architecture School, Civil War General Howard, Harold Ickes, Founders Library (Howard U.), father reported corruption (building materials), father fired, father sued Howard U., U.S. Supreme Court, Howard settled, Cornell University, School of Architecture, drafted World War II, Francis Deal, Ed Morton, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (RPI), professional African–American community in D.C., Federal Government – non-discrimination hiring, housing discrimination, father's proposed 500-acre town (Calvert Town), Chesapeake Bay, Cambridge, MD, Prince Frederick, MD, Senator Carter Glass, Harold Ickes (Secretary of Interior), Bureau of Yards & Docks, Veterans Administration, General Services Administration, Julius Hobson, Birmingham, Alabama, CORE (Congress of Racial Equality), James Farmer, 9th & S Streets NW, Capital Transit Co., no black motormen/bus drivers, O. Roy Chalk, Bruce Hunt haberdashery - 9th & F, "Don't buy where you can't work", whites, blacks picketed, Washington Hospital Center, Afro American newspaper, The Tribune, Washington Star, Washington Post, Walter Washington, professional black community, arrests, Hobson new organization, after CORE -- Associated Community Teams, D.C. Board of Education, D.C. Statehood Party, D.C. Council of Black Architects, Walter Washington, Albert I. Cassell (Cassell's father), Hahn's shoe store, D.C. Commissioners, Army Engineers Corps, rats removal program Ward 3 Georgetown, Hobson campaign to distribute rats into white communities, seeking rat abatement funds black community, Georgetown, rally - plaza (now Freedom Plaza), honor to be arrested, anti-freeway, ECTC (Emergency Committee on the Transportation Criss), Sammie Abbott, D.C. City Council, Takoma Park, Brookland, ECTC, freeway picketing, 3 Sisters Bridge, surrounded 3 Sisters site, Sammie Abbott's office, Dupont Circle Building, Poster: White Men's Roads through Black Men's Houses, unboarded houses in Brookland, Chief Jerry Wilson, white people aided, stopped freeway, Angela Rooney, Tom Rooney, Washington Post opposed to D.C. Constitution, D.C. Constitutional Convention, Walter Fauntroy, Republican committee member, David Clarke, Gloria Corn, D.C. Statehood Convention, Shadow Senators, Shadow Representative, Michael Brown (Shadow Senator), Albert Cassell, son was a rabble-rouser, School Board, Marion Barry, PRIDE, Inc., minor conflicts with Barry, Verizon Center, WorldCom, D.C. Historic Preservation Review Board (HPRB), Mayor Sharon Pratt Kelly, chairman HPRB, historic district (Verizon Center area), Cassell opposed Verizon Center, Barry didn't reappoint, home rule, "home fool", Josephine Butler, Hilda Mason, Reginald Booker, D.C. Statehood Party, Sammie Abbott, Abbott arrested often, later mayor Takoma Park, Josephine Butler, Paul Robeson Society, Hilda Mason, Hobson legislation for statehood, Walter Washington, Sen. Ted Kennedy, Rep. Fred Schwengel, D.C. Statehood Constitutional Convention, Hilda Mason, Josephine Butler, Hilda Mason, up for chair, Hilda married to Charlie Mason, Hilda seen as not forceful, Cassell, chair convention, Cassell as "go-getter", Betty Ann Kane, 90-days and $250,000 funded, redlining, Federal City College, Washington Technical Institute, Washington Teacher's College, University of the District of Columbia (UDC), Washington Board of Trade, Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corp., Riggs Bank, Perpetual S&L, American Security Bank, jazz, Howard Theater, Charlin Jazz Society, Linda Wernick, Billie Holiday, Ella Fitzgerald, Lowell Thomas, Tom Mix, Fats Waller, Erskine Hawkins, Willie Bryant, Redd Foxx, Ella Fitzgerald, Pearl Bailey, Bill Bailey, Georgie Auld, DC Arts and Humanities Council, Washington Ethical Society, Buck Hill, Tito Puente, Linda Wernick, Dizzy Gillespie, Jazz Centennial, Kennedy Center, Alice Bonner, Duke Ellington, Duke Ellington Centennial, Mercer Ellington, Nicholas Brothers, Louis Armstrong Tribute concert, Wynton Marsalis, Duke Ellington, Wolf Trap, Jazz cruises on Potomac, 1977 – The Jazz Arts Society, John Eaton, Sarah Vaughan, Kirk Stuart, Linda Wernick, Charlin Jazz Society, Cardozo High School, Millennium Stage, Kennedy Center, National Public Radio (NPR), Anne Loikow, Ward 3 4th of July parade, Jazz Cruise on the Potomac, Nap Turner, "Going Down Slow" (song)
- Interview: Clark, Steve, 2019 May 10; MS2388
  Steve Clark went through many stages of activism. He was a protester, revolutionary, and organizer. Locally he is best known as the driving force behind Stone Soup, a non-profit food store in Adams-Morgan.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Steve Clark interview: Military family, Air Force Academy 1965-67, Columbia University, Georgetown University January 1968, LBJ won't run, MLK death, aftermath, teaching math, Kent State, revolutionary, despair, Bobby Seale, GW Law School, No Business As Usual, arrested, GLUT food coop, Stone Soup, volunteers, summer 1973, employees, collectives, alternative community, post-shift meetings, Marxism, Marxist study groups, end of Stone Soup, Baltimore, New Communist Movement, Chinese Communism, Communist Workers Party 1979, KKK versus CWP, Greensboro NC march, Ohio for 7 years, community organizer, back to mainstream, back to Washington DC, teaching, writing, socialism versus corporations, social media.
- Interview: Columbia Road Children's Center, 2017 April; MS2388
  Scope and Contents
  Three staff members (Paulette Saunders, Susie Solf, Faye Allen) from Columbia Road Children's Center in the early 1970s talk about getting their jobs, the ideology of the school, and the long term effects of this multicultural experience on the lives of the students and staff.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Columbia Road Children's Center interview: Paulette Saunders, interview, Barbara Chambers, Susie Solf, choosing a school, white opening, Faye Allen, a real teacher, history, 1/3 1/3 1/3, multicultural, food choices, community events, play-based, preparation for Grade 1, music, gathering time, songs from all over, what became of the graduates, internationalists, lawyers, doctors, civic minded, lifetime legacy
- Interview: Dekker, Onka and Sue Solf (Phillips), 2016 November 15; MS2388
  Onka and Susie discuss some of their experiences with the Earth Onion women's improvisational theater group.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Onka Dekker and Susie (Solf) Phillips interview: Susie Solf, Onka Dekker, Earth Onion, December, 1970, All Souls Church, rehearsals, Kathy Hadid, National Liberation Front, play about Vietnam, anti-war and feminist, Improv, 3-4 years, tie-dyed t-shirts, tour, the South, Vermont, in a van, "Woman Potion", Lynn Ditchfield, be a watermelon, Charlotte Bunch.
- Interview: Drew, James, 2017 January 30; MS2388
  James (Jim) Drew is a lawyer who embedded himself deeply into the civil rights movement, the anti-war movement, and the city of Washington, DC after moving here in 1968. He served two four-year terms as president of the local chapter of the National Lawyers Guild and was legal counsel for the Black Panthers. Jim remains politically active with NLG.
  Keywords provided by the donor for James Drew interview: National Lawyers Guild (NLG), Thurgood Marshall, Black Panther defense in DC and VA, NLG role at 1968 Democratic Convention, May Day, other events, Infiltration of NLG in Washington DC, Meeting in Vietnam with 500 Vietnamese lawyers, 1965 visit to SNCC in Mississippi as consciousness-changer, Marriage to human rights lawyer Severina Rivera, NLG target for Counter-Intelligence Program (Cointelpro).
- Interview: Dugan, James, 2012 December 21; MS2388
  Hyattsville native who was Local 6 president in pressmen's 1975-1977 strike at Washington Post.
  Keywords provided by the donor for James Dugan interview: Katherine Graham, Eugene O'Sullivan, Sharon Rose, Fred Solowey, Riverdale, MD, Hyattsville, MD, Greenbelt, MD, Riverdale City Council, Ireland, 3 brothers, 2 sisters, Bricklayers Union, Archbishop John Carroll High School, (Mary) McGregor -- wife, 5 children, Washington Daily News, Labor Press, Washington Star, Wall Street Journal, Washington Post, Eugene Meyer, Larry Wallace, Larry Kennelly, Post reprimand letters to homes, status quo – clause in contract, cost of living, Padilla affair, Mike Padilla, wildcat strike, John Prescott, SWAT team, targeted by Post, school for scabs, Southern Production Program, Inc. (SPPI), a/k/a school for scabs", Newspaper Guild, strike for excellence, Carl Bernstein, Bob Woodward, Walter Pincus, open warfare, contract expired, strike authorization, superficial damage (to presse), former noses (parts of the presses), Goss Printing Press Company, scabs, helicopters, White House, Russian Embassy, Teamsters, Channel 5, Roy Meachum, Earl Silbert, indictments, grand jury, 5th amendment, Post anti-union propaganda, grand jury, John Klauss, suicide, workman's compensation, blacklist, Baltimore, grand jury – 100 strikers subpoenaed, David Rein, Joe Forer, no "grand conspiracy", final offer, working conditions, manning restrictions, Katharine Graham: "slit my throat", Charlie Davis, Stereotypers Union, scabs, Plan X (to break strikes), Newspaper Guild, Mailers Union, Charley Scott, Paperhandlers Union, Stereotypers, printers' union, Hubert Humphrey, George McGovern, Roy Meachum, Monsignor George G. Higgins ("labor priest"), D.C. City Council, Davy Marlin-Jones, George Meany, AFL-CIO, Electricians Union, Donald Graham, Mark Meagher, Larry Wallace, Jack McIntosh, Rep. John Conyers, Channel 5 News, Village Voice, "All the President's Men", Kennedy Center, "We Shall Overcome", Dustin Hoffman, Ray Foreman, Ray Collins, Jimmy Ingraham, Charlie Davis, Raffo, wife – Mary Dugan, Fred Solowey, "the left", Irv Riskin, Paul Baker, communists, "good communists", "bad communists", Brint Dillingham, Sam Pizzigati, John Hanrahan, Hari Krishna, Chip Berlet, National Council of Churches, D.C. Council, Fred Solowey, strike play - Chip Berlet, People's Grand Jury, Josephine Butler, Pressman's International, Sol Fishko, strike benefits, Post lawsuit, Jimmy Hoover, $15 million damage suit, Irv Riskin, boycotts, mortgaged house, Dugan liquor store - New Carrollton, Other Dugan liquor store (Capitol Hill), moved to Florida, auto body shop, towing business, Mary Dugan, Local 6 Defense Committee, Chile solidarity, Letelier-Moffitt memorial march, Labor Alliance, Ralph Nader, health/safety tests, Washington Star, Local 6 (Pressmen's), Brint Dillingham, union card, strike situations - Miami, Detroit, high school graduates, Teamsters, Progressive Magazine, (Metropolitan) Labor Council, Newspaper Guild, Labor Film Festival, Dan Dugan, PATCO, liberals, the Reagans, big money for CEOs, Michigan – right-to-work state, Local 6, government unions, Firefighter's Union, emergency medical technicians, complete controls, manning clauses, speed-ups, well-planned assault (on unions), not automation, printers.
- Interview: Eisner, David, 2013 June 28; MS2388
  U. of Maryland activist during antiwar blockade of Route 1; then owner of head shop Maggie's Farm and boutique until the early 1970s; and owner House of Musical Traditions in Takoma Park since the early 1970s.
  Keywords for David Eisner interview provided by the donor: House of Musical Traditions, Institute of Musical Traditions, University of Maryland, Maggie's Farm, West Orange, N.J., New York City, Competitive swimmer, University of Maryland, 1966, Swim Coach (Bill) Campbell, Cole Field house, Anne Arundel Hall, Students supported pro-war position, U. Md. conservative campus 1966, U. Md. transformed politically by 1970, Women's dorms, men's dorms 1966, By 1970 co-ed dorms, Denise Levertov, Allen Ginsberg, Speakers against the war, racism, Workers' rights, Students for Democratic Society, Democratic Radical Union of Maryland (DRUM), Narcs, Maryland large military industrial complex, Maryland campuses — Germany, Vietnam, ROTC, McKeldin Library, Route 1, Closing off Route 1, SWAT team, Halftracks, jeeps, teargas, Pepper spray, Shotguns with rock salt, National Guard, Midnight curfew, Dunkin' Donuts, Prince Georges County police, Inter Fraternity Council, Booked concerts Cole Fieldhouse, Sly and the Family Stone, The Dells, "Stay", Armory, Skinner Building, "The Skinner 87", ROTC Building Burned, Maggie's Farm, 1 Columbia Avenue, Takoma Park, military draft ping-pong ball lottery, Beatles #9, Anti-draft centers, Asthma, Hay fever, 1-Y classification, Canada, McGill University, Candlemaking business, Ex-Wax, Maggie's Farm, Pipes, Rolling papers, The Still Point, Incense, Unisex fashions, The Hind Quarter leather shop, Holsters, water beds, Yes bookstore, Meditation, Vegetarian cooking, New Jersey Symphony, Liz Meyer & Friends, J.B. Morrison, Saggita SP??, Childe Harold, Emmylou Harris, House of Musical Traditions, 7040 Carroll Avenue, Takoma Park, Vegetarians, 7th Day Adventists, Arts community, House of Musical Traditions, New York, Appalachian lap dulcimers, Jean Ritchie, L. Ron Hubbard, Scientologists, African thumb piano, Irish bodhran, Greenwich Village, Clubs' no-alcohol sections, John Coltrane, Pharaoh Sanders, Ornette Coleman, East-West fusion sounds, Takoma Cafe, Takoma Park-Silver Spring Food Cooperative, 1981 concerts began, Old Takoma Business Association, Voting rights 16-year-olds, Nuclear-free zone, Drug-free chickens, Takoma Park folk festival, Sammie Abbott, Pete Seeger, Metro, Clarksville, Md., Big Bad Wolf, Soupergirl, Busboys and Poets, Dave Van Ronk.
- Interview: Fenty, Jan Pergol and Susie Solf (Phillips), 2016 November 15; MS2388
  Jan and Susie discuss their experiences in the Women's Movement during 1968-1971.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Jan Pergot Fenty and Susie (Solf) Phillips interview: Susie Solf, Jan Pergot Fenty, 1968-1971, consciousness raising, married, having children, office on Biltmore Street NW, witty, acting up at Garfinkles, hexed the cosmetics, spells in front of the Capitol, Susie civil rights background, Leftist, Communist, SNCC, None had jobs, Food stamps, Unemployment insurance, Women's welfare rights, Healthcare, Abortion, Marxist Leninist Study Group, Both Susie and Jan were pregnant, Boy babies banned from party, Lesbian take-over, Marriages break up, Susie and Jan leave group, Group withers, Susie starts women's theater, Jan has another baby.
- Interview: Freeway Forum, 2013 September 12; MS2388
  Keywords provided by the donor for Freeway Forum interview: Angela Rooney, Brookland neighborhood leader in Emergency Committee on Transportation Crisis, Arturo Griffiths, DC Jobs with Justice, Parisa Narouzi, Empower DC, Andria Swanson, Ivy City Civic Association, Derrick Nabors, Amalgamated Transit Union, Local 689, Moderator: John Hanrahan, writer and former executive director of The Fund for Investigative Journalism.
  Angela Rooney, Brookland neighborhood leader in Emergency Committee on Transportation Crisis, Arturo Griffiths, DC Jobs with Justice, Parisa Narouzi, Empower DC, Andria Swanson, Ivy City Civic Association, Derrick Nabors, Amalgamated Transit Union, Local 689, Moderator: John Hanrahan, writer and former executive director of The Fund for Investigative Journalism.
- Interview: Golde, Madeleine, 2015 Janury 23; MS2388
  Came to Washington, DC in 1967 in the era of President Johnson's Great Society programs to try to make a difference in terms of social programs for the poor. During her seven years in HEW, she was an outspoken activist against the war in Vietnam within the federal bureaucracy, including helping to form government-wide anti-war organizations; launched an underground newspaper that circulated widely throughout the Dept for 5 years, tackling issues ranging from treatment of minorities in HEW, to effectiveness of HEW programs and free speech rights for employees; and helped and played an important role in activating a moribund union local in her Department. For the past 40 years, she has continued to be an active participant in advocating for the rights of workers and the protection of our communities.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Madeleine Golde interview: Madeleine Golde, 1967, President Johnson, Great Society Program, U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare, HEW, outspoken activist against the war in Vietnam, federal bureaucracy, The Advocate, effectiveness of HEW programs, federal employees, social work and community organization, community organizer, working with low-income people, change in national social policy, anti-war organizing, working on poverty issues, young people going into the government, social change, federal service as a way of making a contribution, Thursday Discussion Group, speaking about problems in federal programs, Toby Moffitt, Rennie Davis, Mike Tigar, Mike Tabor, federal employee petition drive against the War in Vietnam in 1967, The Advocate started in 1968, Petition drive throughout the government, speaking out against the War, fear in the federal government, Hatch Act, education federal employees, wearing buttons, Washington Post, Washington Star, April 1968 printed petition against the War in Vietnam, word of mouth passing around the petition, Mike Ambrose, Chuck Moran, Peter Schenck, I.F.Stone, Federal Employees meet to organize, White House, identifying federal employee leaders, unprecedented event in the federal government, difficulty with bosses, reprimands by bosses, reprimands by the government agencies, money going to the war effort, money that should be going to fight poverty, federal underground paper, employee run paper looking at federal programs, need to be more outspoken about programs not working, February 1968 first issue of The Advocate, mimeographed newspaper, upward mobility in the federal government, Secretary Elliott Richardson, racism in the federal government, racism in HEW, Moratorium activities in federal government, federal programs in Appalachia, President Nixon, Welfare reform programs, President Nixon's State of Union, popular paper in the department, agency underground paper, Rainbow Sign at NIH-NIMH, payment for The Advocate, Editorial staff, Local 41American Federation of Government Employees, AFGE, Central Payroll, U.S. Bond drive in HEW, Anti-Bond drive, Golden List of Non-Subscribers, grievances in the federal government, Mary Ellen Sacco, John Saunders, Betsy Erb, Gary Grassl, David Knudsen, Jeffrey Starkweather, Make programs better, Office of Internal Security, FBI, Federal Employees for Peace, demonstration at the Capitol, FOIA, union organizing, young people coming into the government, moribund federal union, Roy Morgan, President of Local 41, activist unions in the federal government, OEO, Library of Congress, Labor Department, workers' rights, Federal Employees for a Democratic Society (FEDS), Organizing around broad social policy issues, Women's Issues, Civil Rights, Federal employees rallies, Lafayette Park, May Day in 1971, federal employees in May Day, Marching to the Capitol, Dr. Spock at NIH in 1970, Dr. Daniel Ellsberg dinner – September 1971, Federal Employees for Peace (FEP), FEP dinner for Dr. Ellsberg, awards dinner, Pentagon Papers, Code of Ethics of Federal Service, Natasha Reatig, Federal Employees for Peace Banner, Press coverage of Daniel Ellsberg, Suing the government over right to speak, Secretary Wilbur Cohen, ACLU, First Amendment issues, changing conditions for federal employees, Expanding consciousness among federal employees, Federal employee discussion groups, Effecting federal programs and policies, Norman Oslik, IPS - Institute for Policy Studies, Workplace organizing, Issues of Health and Safety, Progressive Cheverly, Ferment in the 60's, Government survellience, Commitment to public service.
- Interview: Gottlieb, Sanford, 2013 April 12; MS2388
  Head of SANE (Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy), which was a major organizer of Vietnam antiwar protests; a key lobbyist in support of the partial nuclear test-ban treaty between the United States and the Soviet Union.